g.26
Ukrainian Historical and Educational Center of NJ Archives
Fr. Gregory Chomicky papers
circa 1913-1975
g.26
Ukrainian Historical and Educational Center of NJ Archives
19.5 Linear feet
This collection houses the personal and professional papers of Fr. Gregory Chomicky, a "first wave" (pre-World War I) Ukrainian immigrant to the United States. It contains material related to his work as a clergyman, both as a parish priest and as a member of the leadership of the Ukrainian Orthodox Church in America and the Ukrainian Orthodox Church of the USA. It also documents his personal and family life as well as parish and Ukrainian-American community activities.
Chomicky, Gregory, 1891-1974
Biographical/Historical note
Fr. Gregory Chomicky (Григорій Хомицький, Hryhorii Khomyts'kyi) was one of the first Ukrainian Orthodox clergymen in the United States. He was a leader of the proto-Orthodox "Ukrainian National Church" in the mid-1910s, and later played a major role in both the Ukrainian Orthodox Church in America and the Ukrainian Orthodox Church of the USA. He helped to found St. Vladimir Ukrainian Orthodox Church in Cleveland (now St. Vladimir Cathedral) and St. Michael parish in Jeannette, Pennsylvania, and served at a number of parishes in Delaware and Pennsylvania from the 1940s through the 1960s.
Fr. Gregory was born on October 11, 1891 in the village of Lubianky Vyshchi near Zbarazh in the Austro-Hungarian province of Galicia (now in Zbarazh raion, Ternopil' oblast', Ukraine) to Mykhailo Khomyts'kyi and Domitselia Adamovych. He completed his secondary education at the Ternopil' Gymnasium in 1911, then studied philosophy at the Franz Joseph Imperial University in L'viv. He emigrated to the United States in February, 1913. He continued his studies at the Roman Catholic seminary of Sts. Cyril and Methodius in Orchard Lake, Michigan, and then (at the request of the Ukrainian Greek Catholic Bishop Soter Ortyns'kyi) at St. Mary Seminary in Baltimore. His formal education was interrupted by illness in the fall of 1914, but he continued his studies independently.
He was ordained to the deaconate and priesthood in May 1915 by the Old Catholic Bishop Carmel Henry Carfora in Youngstown, Ohio, and was named Vicar General of the Ukrainian National Church. Due to concern about Bishop Carfora's canonicity, Fr. Gregory was re-ordained by Bishop Stephen Dzubay of the Russian Orthodox Mission in 1918. Fr. Gregory joined the eparchy of Archbishop Ioan (Teodorovych) upon his arrival in the United States in 1924. In the 1930s, he changed his allegiance to Bp. Bohdan (Shpyl'ka) of the Ukrainian Orthodox Church in America.
The late 1940s saw major changes in the landscape of Ukrainian Orthodoxy in North America, precipitated in part by the arrival of large numbers of post-war Displaced Persons, which, in contrast to previous immigration waves, included significant numbers of Orthodox Christians from central and eastern Ukraine. Among the refugees were Orthodox bishops such as Mstyslav (Skrypnyk) and Ilarion (Ohienko), and many Orthodox clergy. Fr. Gregory was literally in the middle of these events. In 1948, a Sobor (general Church Council) took place at the cathedral in Allentown, Pennsylvania, where he was the rector. This Sobor ratified the appointment of Abp. Mstyslav (then with the Ukrainian Greek Orthodox Church of Canada) to join Bp. Bohdan's eparchy. Fr. Gregory was heavily involved in the preparations for the Sobor, as well as with its aftermath (Bp. Bohdan and some priests and parishes did not go along with the Council's decisions and friction developed between him and the governing board of the Church). In 1950, joint Sobors of the Ukrainian Orthodox Church in America and the American Ukrainian Orthodox Church of the USA met in New York City, followed by an Extraordinary Sobor which unified the two Churches to form the present Ukrainian Orthodox Church of the USA (UOC of USA). Fr. Gregory remained with the UOC of USA until his death in 1974.
Fr. Gregory served as parish priest at Holy Trinity parish, Chicago (1915-1916, 1924); Sts. Peter and Paul Croatian Byzantine Catholic parish, Chicago (1916-1924, 1930-1937); St. Vladimir parish, Cleveland (circa 1925-1930); Buffalo, NY (1930); St. Michael parish, Jeannette, Penn. (1937-1939); Sts. Peter and Paul parish, Wilmington, Del. (1939-1941); the Ukrainian Orthodox Church of the Most Holy Mother of God, Allentown, Penn. (1941-1950); the Ukrainian Orthodox Church of St. Volodymyr, Ambridge, Penn. (1950-1954); and St. Michael parish, Scranton, Penn. (from 1954 until his retirement).
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open for researcher use. Please contact the archivist (archives@ukrhec.org) for more information and to make arrangements.
Custodial History
After the death of Fr. Gregory, the collection resided with his widow and his daughter Elaine Chomicky White. The collection arrived in the Center in the form of three accruals. The first consisted of photocopies made by Elaine White of portions of the professional records (these make up the bulk of the current Series 12). She subsequently donated the originals of those records, which make up most of the current Series 1. The rest of the collection remained in the custody of Elaine White, and were donated to the Center by her nephew (Fr. Gregory's grandson) John Tockston acting as her power-of-attorney.
Зміст фонду
Цей фонд включає в собі особисті та професійні документи о. Григорія Хомицького, іммігрант "першої хвилі" до США. Фонд містить матеріали, пов'язані з його діяльністю як настоятелем парафій, і як член керівництва Української Православної Церкви в Америці та Української Православної Церкви в США. У фонді також особисті та сімейні листи та документи, а також матеріяли про громадську та парафіялну діяльність українців в Америці.
Фонд містить кореспонденцію, протоколи зборів та церковних соборів, рукописи, проповіді, парафіяльні матеріяли (метрики хрещення та шлюбу, церковні оголошення), фотографії, газетні вирізки, та публікації.
Ця колекція відрізняється тим, що вона містить значну кількість матеріалу, яка документує критичний період 1948-го до 1950-го року в історії Української Православної церкви в США. Вона також містить листи та інші документи, пов'язані з життям українців в Америці в 1910-х і 1920-х роках, період з якого первинні джерела досить рідкісні. Метричні записи, шлюбні оприлюднення, і подібні матеріяли з українських і хорватських церковних громад Чикаго та Аллентаун, штат Пенсільванія, також будуть допоміжні генеалогам.
Scope and Contents
This collection houses the personal and professional papers of Fr. Gregory Chomicky, a "first wave" (pre-World War I) Ukrainian immigrant to the United States. It contains material related to his work as a clergyman, both as a parish priest and as a member of the leadership of the Ukrainian Orthodox Church in America and the Ukrainian Orthodox Church of the USA. It also documents his personal and family life as well as parish and Ukrainian-American community activities.
The collection contains correspondence, minutes, Church Council (Sobor) records, manuscripts, sermons, parish records (such as records of baptism and marriage, as well as notes of church announcements and marriage banns), photographs, newspaper clippings, ephemera, published materials, and realia.
This collection is distinctive in that it contains significant quantities of material documenting the critical period in Ukrainian Orthodox church history from 1948 to 1950, and will therefore be of interest to religious historians of. It is also unusual in that it contains letters and other documents relating to Ukrainian-American life in the 1910s and 1920s, a time period which in general is poorly documented in terms of primary sources. The collection has correspondence, ephemera, and photographs related to Ukrainian-American cultural events in Cleveland, Ohio in the 1920s and early 1930s, including community participation in the "All Nations Exposition" and the "Theater of the Nations". Notebooks containing church announcements provide a unique snapshot of the daily life of Ukrainian Orthodox parishes in the 1950s and 1960s. The sacramental records, marriage banns, and related materials will also be of considerable interest to genealogists.
Arrangement
Arranged in twelve series as follows
Professional records and correspondence
Personal and family correspondence
Subject files
Writings
Church announcements and notes
Parish records
Address books, notebooks, and diary
Photographs
Ephemera and newspaper clippings
Books and other published materials
Realia
Photocopies
American Ukrainian Orthodox Church of the USA.; Bilon, Peter, 1879-1959; Bohdan (Shpylka), Metropolitan, 1892-1965; Hundiak, Ivan, 1895-1985; Mstyslav, Patriarch of Kiev and All Ukraine, 1898-1993; Old Catholic Church in America.; Teodorovych, Ivan, Metropolitan, 1887-1971; Ukrainian Orthodox Church in America.; Ukrainian Orthodox Church of the USA.; Croatian Americans--Illinois--Chicago; Registers of births, etc.; Sermons; Sermons, Croatian; Sermons, Ukrainian; Ukrainian American churches; Ukrainian Americans--Illinois--Chicago; Ukrainian Americans--Ohio--Cleveland; Ukrainian Americans--Pennsylvania
- Professional records and correspondence, circa 1915-1971; Series 1.; 2.75 Linear feet
  Scope and Contents
  Correspondence and records associated with Fr. Gregory's work as a priest and member of national-level Church leadership. Includes incoming and copies of outgoing correspondence with bishops Carmel Henry Carfora, Ioan (Teodorovych), Joseph (Zuk), Bohdan (Shpyl'ka), and Mstyslav (Skrypnyk); correspondence with Church Consistory and Board; correspondence with fellow clergy (most prominently Fr. Andrii Ivanyshyn, Fr. Petro Bilon, and Fr. Ivan Hundiak) and laity; parish-related correspondence and records; certificates; mailings from the UOC of USA Consistory; records related to Sobors (Church Councils); correspondence with and manuscripts from the editorial office of the periodical "Ukrains'kyi Vistnyk"; deanery records and mailings; and related materials. Additional or unusual materials are noted at the file level.
  Arrangement
  Arranged primarily by date, except for some subject-based groupings that reflect what appears to be the original order.
  Related Archival Materials
  Given the difficulty of separating personal from professional material in the papers of members of the clergy, researchers should also consult the "Personal and family correspondence" series in this collection.
  - circa 1915-1919, 4 folders (Box 1, Folder 1-4)
  - 1920-1929, 6 folders (Box 1, Folder 5-9)
  - 1930-1940, 5 folders (Box 1, Folder 10-11, Box 2, Folder 1-3)
    Also includes undated materials, incidental prayer and speech, archpastoral letters by Bp. Bohdan (some in holograph), and newspaper clippings and other published materials.
  - 1940, 1946 (bulk 1940), 2 folders (Box 2, Folder 4-5)
  - 1941 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - 1942 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - 1943 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    Also includes item from 1942.
  - 1944 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - 1945 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Also includes donor lists and letters and telegrams of greeting for a banquet honoring Bp. Bohdan and celebrating the Allentown parish's "mortgage burning".
  - 1946 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - 1947, 2 folders (Box 3, Folder 1, Box 2, Folder 12)
    Also includes material dated 1942.
  - 1942-1950 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    Also contains eparchial financial statements and parish sacramental register book extracts for Allentown, PA.
  - Consistory meeting minutes, 1944-1947 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Displaced Person clergy, 1945-1950; 2 folders (Box 3, Folder 4-5)
    Contains letters from clergy in Displaced Persons camps in Germany seeking help from the Ukrainian Orthodox Church in America (addressed to Fr. Ivanyshyn and Fr. Forostii), along with their biographical information, IRO certificates, and related documentation. Also includes correspondence related to the resettlement of Abp. Ilarion (Ohienko), and publications by the Ukrainian Congress Committee of America, the United Ukrainian American Relief Committee, and the newsletter of the Ukrainian prisoner of war camp in Rimini, Italy.
  - 1948 and 1950 Sobors, 1947-1950; 0.75 Linear feet 21 folders (Box 3, Folder 6-12, Oversize 1, Box 5, Folder 1-4, Box 4, Folder 1-9)
    Primarily contains materials pertaining to the preparation, activity, and aftermath of the 1948 and 1950 General Church Councils (Sobors) which lead to the creation of the present Ukrainian Orthdox Church of the USA. It includes correspondence, meeting minutes, Sobor minutes, and messages of support and dissent sent to the Sobor. It also includes materials related to legal disputes between the Board of the Ukrainian Orthodox Church in America and Bp. Bohdan, and letters to Ecumenical Patriarch Athenagoras regarding the Board's dissatisfaction with Bp. Bohdan. Some folders contain materials dated 1941 to 1946. It also contains some incidental materials related to general Church administration and parish business during the this time period.
  - 1951-1959, 13 folders (Box 5, Folder 5-10, Box 6, Folder 1-7)
  - Fr. W. Fedak correspondence, 1954 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    Correspondence with Fr. Fedak of Hamilton, Ontario. Fr. Fedak is requesting information missionary work done by Fr. Gregory in Hamilton in the 1920s for use in a parish anniversary book. Also includes items related to Hamilton, Ontario dated 1926.
  - St. Michael parish (Scranton, Penn.) and UOC of USA Consistory, 1958-1962 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    Contains correspondence related to disputes between the parish and the Consistory of the Ukrainian Orthodox Church of the USA.
  - 1960-1971, 7 folders (Box 7, Folder 1-5, Box 6, Folder 10-11)
  - Undated (Box 7, Folder 6)
    Contains handwritten notes of meetings, possibly from the 1930s and/or 1940s.
- Personal and family correspondence, circa 1913-1969; Series 2.; 1.2 Linear feet
  Given the difficulty of separating personal from professional material in the papers of members of the clergy, researchers should also consult the "Professional records and correspondence" series in this collection.
  Arranged chronologically by decade.
  Contains letters and postcards from individuals throughout the US and Canada, as well as from family members in inter-war Galicia, Poland (Kalisz), Austria (Vienna), and Czechoslovakia (Terezín and Liberec/Reichenberg).
  - circa 1913-1919, 2 folders (Box 7, Folder 7-8)
  - 1920-1929, 3 folders (Box 7, Folder 9, Box 8, Folder 1-2)
  - 1930-1939, 2 folders (Box 8, Folder 3-4)
  - 1940-1949, 4 folders (Box 9, Folder 1-3, Box 8, Folder 5)
  - 1950-1969, 2 folders (Box 9, Folder 4-5)
  - Undated (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Holiday greeting cards, circa 1920-circa 1960 (Box 9, Folder 7)
- Subject files, 1927-1975; Series 3.; 0.75 Linear feet
  - Cleveland cultural events, 1927-1931; 3 folders
    Contains materials related to Ukrainian-American cultural events in Cleveland, including concerts, dance performances, the "All Nations Exposition", and the "Theater of the Nations". Includes correspondence with the City of Cleveland, the Cleveland Plain Dealer, the Cleveland Press, and other individuals; photographs; programs and other ephemera; theater seating charts; blueprint of the layout of the "All Nations Exposition"; and period accounts in the English and Ukrainian press.
    - Correspondence, photographs, and ephemera, 1927-1931 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - "Cleveland All Nations Exposition" program book, 1929 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Seating charts, exhibit blueprint, and newspaper clippings (Oversize 2-3, Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Personal documents and certificates, 1925-1965
    - Family documents, 1928-1950 (Box 10, Folder 4, Oversize 4)
      Contains certificates, diplomas, and other personal documents and ephemera.
    - Certificate from the All-Ukrainian Church Council of the Ukrainian Autocephalous Orthodox Church (Kyiv, Ukrainian SSR), 1925 (Oversize 5)
    - Resolution of appreciation from Sts. Peter and Paul Church (Chicago), 1936 (Oversize 6)
    - Certificate from St. Michael Parish (Scranton, Penn.), 1965 (Oversize 7)
  - Golden Anniversary Testimonial Dinner, 1965; 5 folders
    Contains material related to the celebration of the 50th anniversary of Fr. Gregory's priesthood.
    - Greetings (Box 10, Folder 5-7)
    - Newspaper clippings and telegrams (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Banquet program and attendee list (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Funeral, 1974-1975; 4 folders (Box 11, Folder 3-6)
    Contains material related to the funeral of Fr. Gregory, including funeral home paperwork, condolence book, condolence cards, and obituaries.
- Writings, 1933-1968 and undated; Series 4.; 2.5 Linear feet
  Contains manuscripts and notes written by Fr. Gregory or by third parties (authorship is unclear in many cases).
  - Sermons for the church year, 1933-1968; 2.0 Linear feet 55 folders
    Arranged according to the Eastern Christian liturgical calendar.
    Contains sermons given at church services for Sundays, church Feast Days, and during Great Lent. Most sermons are dated with the year in which they were written. Many are also annotated with additional years, presumably indicating the years in which that sermon was "re-used" (presumably at a different parish).
    - Sundays after Pentecost, 32 folders (Box 13, Folder 1-11, Box 11, Folder 7-9, Box 12, Box 14, Folder 1-7)
      Sermons for the 1st through the 32nd Sunday after Pentecost.
    - Paschal cycle, 18 folders (Box 15, Folder 1-9, Box 14, Folder 8-16)
      Sermons from the Sunday of the Publican and Pharisee through Pentecost, including the Sundays of Lent and Easter.
    - Immovable feasts, 5 folders (Box 16, Folder 1, Box 15, Folder 10-13)
      Contains sermons for Nativity season (from the Sunday of the Holy Forefathers through the Sunday after Theophany), Civil New Year, and various Saint's and Feast Days.
    - Great Lent (Box 16, Folder 2)
      Contains sermons for mid-week services during Great Lent, as well as sermons for Lenten "mission" events.
  - Sermons for special occasions, 1941-1951 (Box 16, Folder 3)
    Contains sermons for occasions not based on the liturgical calendar, including Memorial Day, Mother's Day, sermon for returning veterans, funeral eulogies (for Ol'ha Basarabova, Lt. Michael Staso, Natalia Hrypevets'ka, and one with an illegible name), and a sermon for radio broadcast.
  - Sermon fragments (Box 16, Folder 4)
    Contains incomplete sermons, detached pages, and notes.
  - "The One Holy Catholic and Apostolic Church" (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - Prayers and liturgical texts (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - "'Know Your Church!' sermons on Church history", 1931-1945 (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - "Catechism or A short exposition of the truths of the Christian Religion", circa 1940-1941 (Box 16, Folder 8)
    Contains the manuscript of the published book, as well as the US Copyright Office registration certificate and letter to Fr. John Hundiak from Abp. Athenagoras commending the catechism.
  - Sunday School materials (Box 16, Folder 9)
    Contains religious education materials of uncertain authorship.
  - "Kofechik - slavna indyians'ka kniahynia" (Box 16, Folder 10)
    Contains holograph manuscript with title page: "Кофечік - славна індиянська княгиня. Правдиве оповіданя про ґенерала De Soto і його жовнірів. З англійського переклав: Гр. Хомицький" ("Kofechik - The glorious Indian princess. A true story of General De Soto and his soldiers. Translated from the English by G. Chomicky")
  - General writings (Box 17, Folder 1)
    Contains autobiographical information, articles, poems, skits, and notes on both religious and secular themes. Most appear to be by Fr. Gregory, but do not have authorship explicitly indicated.
  - Third-party writings (Box 17, Folder 2)
- Church announcements and notes, 1920s-1967; Series 5.; 0.25 Linear feet
  - Announcement and address book, likely 1920s (Box 17, Folder 3-4)
    Notebook containing announcements to be read to the congregation during Sunday and Holy Day services (announcements of parish activities, donations, and related information), as well as addresses of parishioners and other notes. Entries are labeled by the Sunday in the Eastern Christian liturgical calendar, and most do not have a year indicated. It appears that the notebook contains entries from both Chicago, Ill. and Cleveland, Oh.
  - Announcements, 1943-1967 with gaps
    Notebooks containing announcements to be read to the congregation during Sunday and Holy Day services. Includes announcements of parish activities, donations, and related information.
    - 1943 September-1945 January (Box 17, Folder 5)
    - 1950 February-September (Box 17, Folder 6)
    - 1958 January-June (Box 17, Folder 7)
    - 1958 June-November (Box 17, Folder 8)
    - 1958 November-1959 February (Box 17, Folder 9)
    - 1959 March-September (Box 17, Folder 10)
    - 1959 September-1960 April (Box 17, Folder 11)
    - 1960 April-September (Box 17, Folder 12)
    - 1960 September-1961 March (Box 17, Folder 13)
    - 1961 March-July (Box 17, Folder 14)
    - 1961 July-1962 January (Box 17, Folder 15)
    - 1962 May-October (Box 17, Folder 16)
    - 1962 October-1963 February (Box 17, Folder 17)
    - 1963 March-December (Box 17, Folder 18)
    - 1964 January-August (Box 18, Folder 1)
    - 1964 August-1965 January (Box 18, Folder 2)
    - 1967 May-December (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - "Sorokousty" notebook, 1957-1958 (Box 18, Folder 4)
    Notebook containing lists of names of deceased individuals who were to be commemorated during services for the departed during Lent. Also contains a newspaper clipping.
  - Marriage banns notebook, 1947-1950 (Box 18, Folder 5)
    Notebook containing information for the reading of marriage banns. Most entries include the names, birth dates, places of baptism, and places of residence of the intended bride and groom, as well as the dates on which the banns were read and the date of the wedding.
- Parish records, 1915-1967; Series 6.
  - Baptismal register, Bulk, 1915-1916; 1915-1924 (Box 18, Folder 6)
    Pages from a register book that were removed from their binding containing records of baptisms at the Holy Trinity Parish (Chicago) from 1915 to 1916, as well as at other locations in Chicago from 1916 to 1924.
  - Marriage register, 1915-1925 (Volume 1, Box 18, Folder 7)
    Ledger book containing marriage records from the Holy Trinity parish, Chicago (1915 and 1916), Sts. Peter and Paul parish, Chicago (1917 to 1924), and Cleveland, Ohio (1925).
  - Baptismal certificate pad, 1915-1921 (Box 18, Folder 8)
    Certificate pad containing stubs for baptism certificates issued between 1915 and 1921 for baptisms performed between 1872 and 1921 (bulk 1900 to 1920). It contains both Ukrainian and Croatian surnames, therefore it likely covers Holy Trinity and Sts. Peter and Paul parishes in Chicago.
  - Name lists, undated (Box 18, Folder 9)
    Two undated sheets of parishioners, donors, or participants in an event or activity.
  - St. Vladimir parish (Cleveland), 1926-1929 (Box 18, Folder 10)
    Handwritten draft of bylaws in English dated 1926, and two receipts.
  - St. Michael parish (Jeannette, Penn.) real estate purchase agreement, 1937 (Box 18, Folder 11)
  - St. Volodymyr parish (Ambridge, Penn.) donation receipts, 1951 (Box 18, Folder 12)
    Receipts, "thank you" letters, and holy cards from the Consistory of the UOC of USA to individual parishioners who contributed to the building fund for St. Andrew Memorial Church in S. Bound Brook, NJ. These were presumably to be distributed to the donors, but never were.
  - Parish bulletins, 1965-1967 (Box 18, Folder 13)
    Parish bulletins from St. Michael's parish (Scranton, Penn.) and St. Andrew's parish (Blakely, Penn.).
  - St. Michael parish (Scranton, Penn.) choir book (Box 18, Box 14)